hello welcome back
this is the second session of the
active lab symposium on june 21st 2021
and we're here in the dot-coms or
communication
organizational unit the goal of
dot coms is to organize the labs
internal projects and activities as well
as to carry out
all forms of communication with external
entities
so it's like our connective tissue and
our neuroectoderm
in a way what has been done so far
is that we've had about 75 live streams
variously on presentations and
participatory discussions
since july 28 2020
and we're taking an active inference
approach to communication
and learning by doing our very first
live stream was on
the paper narrative as active inference
and
shortly after a world unto itself human
communication
as active inference so that's something
that we
like thinking about here and that we
want to explore
and also some of our lab members
framed online communication and team
collaboration
in terms of active inference in the 2020
paper active inference and behavior
engineering
for teams our aim here is to make active
inference
accessible well-known and well
understood
so let's get right to the questions carl
the first question is how can we show
not tell
the idea of active inference for example
through embodied experience
experiments or what other mechanisms how
can we best communicate
in a way that makes it resonate
um well pursuing that very interesting
notion of using the principles of active
inference to
optimize the role of the dot coms
team um then
at its simplest active inference means
that
the imperatives for all behavior and
it's likely that
most behavior is of an epistemic
sort is to resolve uncertainty so if you
want to engage people
um and be a um a service
um to the people you want to engage
which may be
um internal members of of your own team
and then you've got to know um what they
don't know um
because that will define the um
the epistemic affordances that will
um get them engaged with you
and you with them um that will um
incur the best kind of belief updating
so um you know practically what that
might mean
is that it may well be that you um one
has to
identify um
didactic or informative
illustrations um that are
tailored or specialized to the person or
people that you're talking about
um so um and then
you know i have never thought about
using embodied experiences before but
that's a brilliant idea you're
[Music]
just illustrating to people who want to
know how my body and my mind
works to you know
illustrate to them you know the
mechanics of
it working
using the language of active inference
it can be very very powerful so as i'm
talking you know
what one example of this would be
um using psychotic suppression
as an illustration of
the potency of getting your beliefs
about the predictability of sensory
evidence right
um so if you're a physiologist um you
would you would know this as sensory
attenuation
if you were in machine learning uh
you're working with transformers this
would be i think
attentional selection um basically
deploying the gain
or switching on the right channels in
order
to select those data that are going to
resolve the most uncertainty or maximize
the
uh the information gain um subsequent
on this sort of covert action or you
know
often sold as a sort of mental action um
in the philosophy literature so that
mental
action um is is really endemic and a
vital part of
our sensory engagement with the world
and beautifully illustrated by sarcanic
suppression so this is the
um speaks to the notion of
um attenuating the sensory consequences
of your own action so that
any evidence that you're not actually
acting is precluded
from your belief updating so a clinical
example of this would be parkinson's
disease for example
if i'm sitting still and i wasn't able
to ignore
all the messages from my muscles that
tell me at the moment i am sitting still
then i am never going to be able to
realize in a priori intention
that i'm going to initiate a movement
because as soon as i initiate a movement
i have
i put in place a plausible hypothesis
that i'm
lifting i'm going to stand up um
immediately all the evidence at hand
suggests that i am not standing up
so i'm going to revise my belief no i'm
not standing up
i'm not in the process of standing up
and it becomes impossible to move
um so that would be an example of what
would happen if you didn't have
this capacity to to or to select
or apply the principles of optimal
bayesian design
in terms of selecting those data for
your own belief
updating but a really pragmatic and easy
example of that is
psychotic suppression when we do the
simplest of movements
um epistemic foraging which is moving
our eyes
making psychedelic eye movements because
when we do that
we actually induce masses of visual
information
on the photoreceptors in the retina uh
sometimes referred to as retinal slip so
when i look from the left to the right
there's a flood of information that i
have caused
and yeah it is not useful information
because
it doesn't tell me anything i didn't
already know so
what the what the brain does it um it it
it suppresses that information by
transiently
suspending the precision if you you're
[Music]
filter like perspective on um predictive
coding as what kind of
um variational filtering um
and that's really easy to to demonstrate
to an audience you know just
get them to to either fixate on
essential
uh stimulus um and then pay attention to
something that's moving around
or the converse they fixate on the thing
that's moving around
and then ask them questions about the
central stimulus and with the right
timing it's a very potent
illustration of um beyond
just gathering information but actively
um
selecting and triaging that information
in accord with the principles of your
optimal optimal days in design
so i haven't thought about going beyond
that but i'm sure there are
lots of lovely um examples um
of embodied experiences that really do
illustrate um
the um the you know active inference in
action as it were
i'm just reminded um
because active inference could be read
as
if you like a um
a 21st century version of ideomotive
theories which were very popular
in in the 19th century and and of course
that was um demonstrated through
embodied experiences in a very alluring
way through hypnotism
and the like so i can i can imagine
suddenly doing a
sort of uh 21st century version of
hypnotism and all those
wonderful victorian illusions about um
you know
the way you use your sense organs or
deploy them actively
and but now in the service of just
illustrating some
basic phenomena that under underwrite
active inference
in terms of experiments or you know
the classic um ones that immediately
come to mind
that are really engaging um are visual
illusions
so on one reading um all visual
illusions are just ways
of getting out your perceptual priors
in the context of of bayesian inference
that you know
if you can conjure a particular pattern
of sensory information
that you know was caused in one way
and yet you think your subject or your
audience
has sufficiently precise prior beliefs
that it could only be caused in another
way
which is not the way you caused it and
then you let them experience that and
then you reveal
how you actually generated those data
then that's a very powerful way
of demonstrating the innate priors the
sort of formal prize in
you know in terms of the connect term or
the um
the the sparse coupling on a on a factor
graph
and the again is part of the lived
experience so i think visual illusions
would be
and there are loads of beautiful
illusions out there and all
that one would have to do is to harness
their
beauty and the law and use them as a
vehicle
to give people insight into the
their own usually sub-personal prize
about the way that the world the world
is constructed
and then um i would i mean in my world
what you generally try and do is to
actually put this in silico by just
you know creating little silicone
creatures
and because you've now got active
imprints with this information geometry
and you you now have the opportunity not
just
to simulate what these creatures do
but what they perceive because now
you've got the um
the quantitative estimates of their
their posterior beliefs so you can
actually show
[Music]
a subject who's just experienced a
visual illusion
that this is perfectly base optimal and
indeed when you write down this
variational message passing scheme in
this synthetic subject
uh this synthetic person also
experiences exactly the same
illusions and this is and this is and
this is per basically
for this kind of kind of work so you can
leverage activities in that sense and
deliberately referring back to the edu
discussions you know
what active inference brings to the
table because it's got information about
stuff
out there in the numerix
you can go a lot further um than you can
if you were doing
say deep learning or machine learning
because you've got this um
this dual you've got this information
geometry at hand
your the state of your variational
autoencoder
actually means something in relation to
a belief about
what generated the those data which you
can create lovely little movies you know
showing what this um simulation of you
um was actually experiencing so
um you know
i'm interested are there are there any
other ways that you you've you've
thought about in terms of
showing people thanks for the answer
it's like look left look right
now you're an active inference agent and
as far as potential avenues
for embodiment some of the work with
ryan smith
and others bringing people into the
somatosensory
dimensions and their own priors and
expectations about their body
and about motion could be very powerful
as well as auditory
modalities and indeed active inference
is a framework by which we can think
about
how our perceptions are related to our
inference and our action
so in various domains i think they'll be
excellent
experiments and it brings us to our next
question
you actually addressed several areas in
your answer
you addressed machine learning as well
as neuroscience as well as
just everyday lived experience so how
can active inference
engage in better dialogue with adjacent
areas
for example machine learning systems
engineering
psychiatry and neuroscience as well as
any other
fields that you think are relevant to
um then you know the obvious answer here
is in
either academic or commercial
collaboration
um and what might you
what would license that um i think
um you know the simplest answer is that
the free energy principle and it's if
you like technological coral reactive
inference
and is not there and was never intended
to um replace uh extant theories it was
there to prove
uh to endorse them and to reveal
the interrelationships between them so
anything that's worked and survived into
the 21st century
has some veracity and a proven utility
and therefore it's just a question of um
reformulating or changing the words
so that people can see immediately um
how
their particular formulation relates to
somebody else's
formulation where both formulations are
special cases
of the most generic and simplest
explanation which would you know from my
point of view would be the
uh the free energy principle and active
inference in the case of
uh sentience so i think that's you know
as an
a an integrative framework you're very
well positioned to say look
you know can we understand the way that
you think about this and
um can we now um articulate this
um either using simulations or you know
mathematical analysis um okay you know
can we understand what you've been doing
in this integrative framework and if we
can um
can we show how it relates to another
disciplines
formulation of this problem and
sometimes you can get
synergistic or added value from doing
that so
you know there must be loads of examples
you've written machine learning systems
engineering psychiatry neuroscience here
so machine learning for example you know
how would active inference help machine
learning
um so at the moment um you know
there seems to be two um answers
um floating around um and we've
we've already sort of discussed a couple
of the uh a couple of the key
a couple of these issues in depth um
so machine learning commits to usually
a normative approach to good behavior
that can be quantified by a loss or a
value
function um but we've just said well if
we now want these machines to learn to
act
then we have to go beyond um state
action
value functions and consider the belief
based calculus that is active inference
which is all about the reduction of
uncertainty so now
you are in a position to say well look
if you
consider your objective functions
as a part of a more generic objective
function
um do you think what you might be able
to get from this
and of course what you might get from
this is a deep learning scheme
that actually can now go and solicit the
right kind of data
to optimize its own learning and you
know people
in bayesian rl might argue well that
yeah that's what we're doing
uh you know with a series of bright
ideas and
and heuristics to try and augment
um classical value functions but
you know you can say well okay you
probably put a lot of work into that
but there is there is actually um you
know a simple objective function already
out there that is
provably um uh to describe
um systems that self-organize and
maintain themselves
that actually has what you want why
don't you try this for example
um so that would be one example you have
to tread carefully because you know
a lot of people have dedicated their
lives to solving these problems and
they're very reluctant to
change their rhetoric or or see their
contributions as a special case
but in many instances um certainly from
my perspective mathematically
they are special cases and sometimes if
you catch the
um the the entrepreneurs the innovators
the creative academics
at the right stage in their career
before they have committed to a
particular church or ideology
or calculus or group or company
and you can you you can actually point
them in the right direction they become
extremely creative and i'm not so sure
about systems engineering but certainly
i always
celebrate um the um
the expected free energy as
with just taking away various bits and
pieces
very sources of uncertainty as um
reducing to um kl control and then what
i say is what chaos control is what
grown-up engineers use
in the control theoretic setting and so
that would be another
example so um you know you could also
i don't know this because it's not my
field but certainly in
in in terms of introducing say a fault
tolerance
in um in control theoretic approaches in
engineering
where the fault tolerance required
uncertainty about the operation of some
external part
you could again motivate a more complete
objective function that
takes you beyond kale control and
introduces the information gain
in your in in into the mix
because to get from the complete
objective function
or to kl control
you have to ignore uncertainty
about the latent states that
are in the mapping from latent states of
the plant you're controlling
to the the the the sensors or the
observables and so you you know you're
moving from a partial observed markov
decision process for example
to an observable one and then um
accepted the energy becomes
kl control or risk sensitive control in
economics so you could you could say
well look you know why did you just
augment the the your kl control
and then put this extra term in and now
what you've got
is is a kind of anticipatory fault
tolerance in the sense that if
if if there's uncertainty about latent
causes that's
automatically resolved in the way that
you um
go and um switch on various sensors or
switch off various sensors as you know
there's a principal way of doing that
i think to have any influence you need
to be able to show or provide proof of
principle
that this um more integrated more um
universal um approach to normative
normative approach to problems um can
offer
um speed ups or increased efficiency or
do what the people
actually in that field wanted to do
so for example you've got to be able to
show that active inference can
outperform
um sort of vanilla deep learning by an
order of magnitude
which is easy to do because of course
most
most benchmarks and machine learning are
actually inference problems
so if you just recast it it's actually
quite quite a trivial
thing to do just by saying well actually
what you've been dealing with
is an inference problem uh which looks a
lot like
a one-shot learning from the point of
view of somebody um
in machine learning but i think there
will be some
pressure to get people's attention
um to make yourself um
attractive in terms of you they will now
have some
first of all um find you
um um interesting um
and also uh have the potential that they
can place an epistemic trust in you
you've got to
you've got to sort of you know give them
a cue a clue and a cue
as to why they should uh should engage
with you and
and very often there's that there's a
two-way
uh two way or two-road exchange
um so one simple example that which i
see emerging in the field is the use
of um um you know so deep learning
to amortize certain mappings um when
they can be amortized in active infant
schemes to evaluate
you know the expected energy for example
or doing very deep
tree searches so that's that's the kind
of innovation you've seen coming out of
20 year olds at the moment who haven't
yet decided whether they're going to do
deep learning or active inference
because they want to do both and do it
very very effectively so that
that's a nice example from my
perspective on the sort of you know that
integrative role
that could be played or you could play
thanks i i really heard this yes and
maxim from communication and
improvisation it's like yes there's been
a disciplinary way of approaching it
and we're going to be working together
to come back to first principles or to
make it more efficient so that's
really powerful
how does active inference help us
rethink the nature of online
communication where so much of our
communication nowadays does occur
that's that's that's a big question
isn't it um
and certainly in the context of um
social media politics fake news and the
like you could you could take that
question in lots of lots of different
directions
which i won't do because that's not my
field of expertise um
but just yeah off the cuff in terms of
first principles and what is
communication
um it's the ability for me to infer what
you meant it's the hermeneutics problem
um if it's a hermeneutics problem that's
most efficiently
um resolved in terms of
um dyadic or multi-system interactions
um when we um come back to first
principles
which is the genetic model when we share
the same narrative or same generative
model
um so
in terms of helping um actually how does
it
um how does active influence help us
rethink the nature of
online communication and i think
just from a first principles point of
view it would be the importance of
establishing who is talking to who
and if you want to optimize the
efficiency of that exchange
literally from the point of view this
principle of least action the speed with
which you can resolve uncertainty and
minimize your uncertainty or surprisal
and then it's ensuring that like-minded
communicators are actually communicating
because it's only them that will
understand each other so everybody has
to speak the same language
they have to commit to a shared
narrative and a shared genetic model
and then just by things like rate
distortion theorem or
you know rewriting that in terms of
active inference
uh 300 min the joint free energy
minimization between
two interlocutors and that's the most
efficient
sort of shared path of least action um
you know
how does that help engineer or um
intervene on things i i'm not so sure
um certainly just in reference to
communications with uh you know people
um people like maxwell and the like and
other colleagues
um there is this interesting notion that
if communication
if the real problem of communication is
not really the messages that you send
but the inferring whether to send the
messages to this person or not
that itself now becomes conditional upon
inferring
that's a member of my in-group or that's
a creature or a person like me
and then the question is um you know
how do how does self-organization say
you know in terms of social media
exchange
how is that underwritten by
an inference about the kind of people
who i
am listening to or who i am talking to
and what are the basic principles of
that and again in accord with
um the minimization of complexity in our
genitive models what we
you know what then it may be a useful
hypothesis
to say that there's an inevitable course
graining
of the way that we conceive of the
people that we
generate information for say on social
media
and reciprocally and the kinds of people
that i will
be able to solicit by listening to this
twitter feed or
that wikipedia page or this news channel
so understanding how people carve up
whether they are like
to the degree of similarity to them
may be very useful in just getting an
idea
of the dynamics of message passing
amongst
amongst communities that will be defined
by
on average how each member of that
ensemble or individual
course grains and has a genetic model of
the kinds of people
in the communication crane and just to
finish this which is
something i've heard and i found it
really interesting notion
um that again would be great if one
could simulate this and understand the
maths behind it
is that the only evolutionary stable
um from the point of view of the free
energy principle the only one that will
be
selected by a processor bayesian model
selection the only
the only partitioning into in groups and
out groups is a 50 50
in group out group and in the sense that
anything that departs from that sort of
um
dynamically unstable but evolutionary
stable partition
means that the smaller group the
outgroup the the the old man
out will necessarily ultimately be
absorbed into the into into the
um into the larger group so the only
the only stable um
um uh partitioning is 50 50 which
which makes a lot of sense when you look
at trump versus biden
when you look at brexit versus not
brexit wherever you look
all the important allegiances
in terms of our political ideological uh
possibly even theological
communication seems to be split right
down the middle and perhaps it can be no
other way so
it'd be very very interesting to
simulate that and see if that is a
truism
that inherits from um all of these
um marginal likelihood or free energy
minimizing
processes implemented at multiple levels
of hierarchical um
multiple hierarchical levels which is
you know communication
is just message passing and message
passing is just the way you articulate
updating and believe updating just is
the process of inference which just is
the the paths of least action according
to the fvp
[Music]
the 50-50 politics it's maximally
confusing
something we all experience and a few
key points there about the nature of
online communication
is that at the core it is dyadic even
when you're broadcasting to many
it's actually about that connection and
the hermeneutic relationship of
unpacking meaning
and then also you brought up the
importance of context and identity and
who's talking to who and our inferences
about that which is essential to
rhetoric and something that often gets
left off when people take big data
approaches
to online discourse the next
question is how does active inference
help us think about science
communication and participation
specifically as we move into
broader citizen science initiatives and
as
scientists are in the loop something
you've been recently involved in as well
with society and with decision making so
as science and the nature of science is
changing
who is doing it and how they communicate
it how does active inference
help us navigate that
right well i'm sure you've thought about
this much more deeply than i have it's
um just drawing upon my experience um
you know in terms of science
communication uh during the
um the coronavirus epidemic yeah i think
you're absolutely right
you can as with the previous questions i
think you can take the principles of
active inference
um and just think about um what does
that mean for optimal communication
and um and belief updating and shared
belief updating and shared narratives or
a lot
um
[Music]
and um use that um
as a point of reference for the way that
you articulate your own science and
you've asked all the
your challenging and exactly right
questions you know about
how you communicate how you engage other
scientists or
other um other partners within or beyond
academia and i think the same principles
apply exactly to
um the the public and just to reinforce
your
i think beautiful observation that all
communication is dynamic from the point
of view of the person communicating
you know so it's this kind of person as
a unitary object i am talking to
or this population or this mentality or
you know so
on this discipline so it is i think
fundamentally
you know dyadic from the point of view
the person generating the messages
um that will uh may or may not
incur belief updating in the recipients
and these kinds of principles i'm sure
would be useful in terms of science
communication
so at that level um i don't know that
there's much
that i would have to what you already
know and you know and will
all and possibly already are
implementing
um there is another level though
which is um using active inference
not as a model for the way that we work
and communicate and participate
but as a um as a more a a
a statistical or observation model of
data
so um in a sense um you can use the
principles of active inference
really to make the most of data
pertinent to a particular domain so
again i'm thinking here of the dynamic
causal modeling
of the epidemiological and behavioral
data
that has been generated by the
coronavirus
epidemic um so um
you you you can you certainly use
the um the perceptual inference side of
it if you like the bayesian filtering
side of it
and but also in principle the um the
data mining or the
you know the the the optimal bayesian
design to select which data are useful
or not
in a very practical way when
assimilating
big data in the service of understanding
the um the system at hand so the system
at hand is
how does a um how does a
um a spike
propagate from one neuron to another
neuron a neural network or
how does a virus propagate from one
person to another person
in a neural population or a network
a population network and then you can
certainly use the data
to um you can apply active inference to
build genetic models of how you think
that occurs
and what immediately comes confronts you
is you've got to put in
all of the things that generate those
data
so you can't miss out any factors um
that are important to be the
psychological be the behavioral
um be they viral be they um
transport related all of these things
have to go into your gender model to
best explain the data so
you know when we do this in a practical
way we we
both use um the instance rates from
pcr testing and google mobility data
and department of transport
transportation data anything
that speaks to them and reduces
uncertainty
about all the factors necessary um
they're entailed by your generative
model in this instance not a discrete
space it's written down oh
no this one is actually a discrete state
space model um
and the active influence is not
explicitly part
of it in the sense that we're not trying
to predict people's behavior
um but it it does serve um an indirect
um guide through the principles of
bayesian optimum
optimum design and all that basically
means is do
i invest computational resources
and thereby incur computational and
statistical complexity
by including or attending to this kind
of data
or not and then you can actually
evaluate
the the the information gain
by including that data of that data so
for example you need
google retail estimates and and or
workplace activity or just one uh
if you include both that means that your
the complexity
increases and your uh literally you have
to wait another half hour before before
you get the results for
your dashboard and or do you
or do you not and have a more
parsimonious um
have a more parsimonious model in the
sense that you have now
in the same sense of that circadic
suppression of retinal slip
and you've actually said no i don't need
that i've got everything i need i got
the right kind of data
just by focusing on these data and then
once you've got that in mind you can now
go
foraging for different kinds of data
different collaborators from different
disciplines
who've got different perspectives but
also crucially
different data you know to try that will
inform
and shrink your uncertainty about the
model parameters
and also very importantly about the
structural form
of the model do i need this node how
many
um is this interaction important or not
is this degree of nonlinearity justified
by the data
so all of these questions affected your
hypotheses about
how this system is responding or would
respond
if you intervene on it all of those
questions now become meaningable
to an evidence-based analysis
because you've got a generative model
underneath the hood
so that would be a more practical
application of um
active the principles that underwrite
active inference even though
your computer program is not actually
doing active inference but it's
certainly been deployed
using the principles of active inference
awesome and we heard that
integrative approach yes we're going to
include multiple
data sets potentially of unconventional
type and
we're going to have a principled way of
deciding how to include that data
and also as you brought up at the end
who to include in the conversation
and there was one piece you said in
there about the dyadic nature
of communication where a speaker is
always
i think you said something like speaking
to a person or to a group or to a
community
and it relates to our next question
which is
how can we appropriately interact with
shared and nested
generative models potentially across
scales
be it person team or community
do we think about these levels of
analysis as
active inference agents in their own
right or how do we
for example speak to a community or
speak to a level of analysis that's
broader than the personal
yeah i think that's
a great and challenging question um i
mean
clearly there has been some provisional
work in academia
uh looking at sort of um mark of
blankets of markov blanket which is
effectively from a
stats point of view from a physics point
of view at least what we're talking
about here
as a physicist um you'll be tackling
this with
things like the renova or the apparatus
of the renormalization group
which tells you immediately something um
interesting that the
existence of um
this nested structure um
[Music]
if underwritten by or if
it is a renormalization group means that
there are certain functional forms that
are conserved
so what that means is from your
practical point of view
that there will be certain kinds of
behavior
um that are actually conserved at
different
scales so what works in terms of
talking to your children should also
work as a president talking to your
community
or a a governor talking to your state
or a team leader talking to your on your
your your assembled team um
simply because um in order for
there to be a hierarchical nesting
um
that supports that hierarchical
structure that has to be this con
conservation usually mathematically
written down as a the functional form of
the lagrangian
um or it could be the sort of martial
likelihood or the surprise
that we're talking about um that
underwrites these sort of um
paths most likely paths or paths of
least action so that
actually paradoxically slightly makes
the problem slightly simpler
because what you're saying is what works
at one level will work at
all levels all you've got to do is um
find the course grading operator
operator that takes you from one level
to the next
um so what that would look like i think
would be very very application domain
specific so
you know i think that there is a great
challenge ahead
which is taking um the single particle
fep
approach now to into a world that
matter where it matters where the world
is actually an ensemble of particles
and we've already discussed the
importance of um
you know thinking about worlds where all
the particles are identical
whereas all the particles actually vote
for half the particles vote for
trump and the other half vote for biden
and this is interesting to reflect upon
um pre-21st century physics
that was so powerful in um articulating
this kind of dynamics because it just
dealt with the simplifying assumption
that my idealized gas
was an ensemble of identical particles
and then you can spin up from that
equilibrium physics and everything that
led
from the um you know from from
carna cycles and and and engines through
to
uh to to to current current technology
so it's a powerful assumption if you
just make some simplifying assumptions
but
just because you know we've already said
well perhaps that's not the best kind of
assumption to make when you're dealing
with political
uh mechanics at least like one bi
partition
in there and so that would require a
revisiting
of the of that kind of um physics
um from our point of view or your point
of view
basically simulating uh active age
inference agents um or ensembles
of active inference agents particles but
where now
there's a heterogeneity in play and then
asking the questions well what are
at the next scale um the free energy
minimizing or surprising minimizing or
potential minimizing
um solutions at the next scale up
so we come back to our you know whys in
the case of people are all split 50 50
which has an enormous impact on the
interactions at the scale below
so i think to tease i think all i'm just
hand waving here because i don't think
there are any
um any formal answers and i think those
formal answers will probably have to
come out of agent-based and possibly
stochastic agent-based
um modeling initiatives but with the
twist
you're making each agent itself an
active inference agent so
while each individual member of the
ensemble is trying to minimize their
free energy
also the ensemble through cooperation
and the shared narrative
is minimizing the joint free energy and
what that means for um when you move
from one scale to the next scale
i you know this is if you if you're in
physics i imagine that this is the
problem
of beyond non-equilibrium
steady states um because you're actually
now
dealing with the multi-scale aspect of
non-equilibrium
so at best we have good models of
turbulent flow and b
center your actions and laser physics
that take us beyond equilibrium physics
where all the particles are the same
um into non-equilibrium physics but i
don't know that there's an equivalent
maths or metaphor in
um um in physics
that would really speak to the the
hierarchical nesting so i think this is
a really
open and important research area that i
can only
recommend is dealt with by numerical
analyses basically
predicated on underlying principles
thanks for the answer there and it made
me wonder if agree to disagree
is a narrative that can be shared even
when there is a 50 50
split and i think it brings us nicely to
the final
question of dot-coms which is
how can we move people and teams into
a co-transformative space or as some of
your
recent work discussed in interactionist
space
well i'm sure you know the answer to
some of these i don't know i suspect now
i'm now realizing you already know the
answers because
you're knowing smiles when i say
something that you recognize but
um so actually answering that from on
the basis of what you just
um what you just said um so yeah i think
that's another really
uh useful insight that you know agreeing
to disagree
is a a surprise minimizing
bayes optimal um explanation
for the exchange with others
and so but it does rest upon committing
to the hypothesis
that you are not like me you are not
like-minded and that's okay
so i've now classified you as somebody
who's not like-minded
and i've resolved the ambiguity in
among the hypotheses that you are either
like-minded or you're not like-minded
normally we resolve those within a few
your first impressions within a few
seconds based upon all these epistemic
cues we offer each other to
define the kind of you know sort of
person that we are so
we make that job as easy as possible for
us and signaling
uh to make this so we know our place and
i i use that phrase because of course
you know
there's a paper called knowing your
place that exploited
um a shared genitive model that allowed
you to be in a particular position
in some space even if you should if you
and i share the same
understanding of political ideology but
i know my place because i'm right-wing
and you your place because you're
left-wing or vice versa
and then we can quite happily exchange
but disa
agreeing to disagree so i think that
that's that's a wonderful um know
perspective to have and to endorse it
and that is a base optional
perspective from both sides of the
disagreement
that's resolving uncertainty and you
know in
a in a bounded rational way
so applying that notion to co-transform
to space it reminds me of the problem
where
certain patients in psychiatry
have committed to a particular inference
about
the you know whether they belong out
there in that kind of environment or not
so that and they have decided um that
they do not belong out there and that
those people are not like them
um and they start to avoid so in a very
simple-minded way and if they're any
psychiatrist
in this example but i think it's
illustrative and useful in that respect
so say take depressive depression or
agrophobia
you know which is a completely baze
optimal
response if i have committed to the
hypothesis
that out there is full of people who are
not like me
and potentially will upset confuse
and render me uncertain and possibly
even injure me in some way
so withdrawal um into that corner of
uh into your house or into that silo
if you're working in you know you know
in teams
is a perfectly based optimal response
that
says that you've got your a precise
belief that this is where you belong
this is this
you know this these are the people that
you speak to and not those people
so and that's usually perfectly
functional um
in psychiatry that would be a neurotic
defense but it can become pathological
um when you become house bound or you
become say if you've got a
pathological hypothesis like your body
got dysmorphophobia and you
you get you know you nearly die because
of
a failure to eat properly so when you
say co-transformative i imagine what you
mean is you want to transform
two teams into uh
one team or at least enable them to work
together
if that's right and you're nodding
partially so
assume that it is uh you're facing the
same challenge
um that a psychiatrist faces
in terms of enabling people to revise
the precision of their price be
precise beliefs about who they can
interact with and who they should
interact with that's not an easy thing
but it's certainly doable and it
basically um
usually reduces to um
presenting evidence to a
a group or a person that it can be
another way so that they start you start
to um revise
their prior beliefs or at least the
precision of their prior beliefs
by in a safe space where it's okay to
explore other hypotheses
um enabling them to think about other
ways of interacting
um so this would normally be the
objective of psychotherapy basically
um to by illustration very much in the
same way
you were talking about sort of you know
illustrating or educating by
embodied experience very much
psychotherapy is thought to work like
this
you provide a psychologically embodied
experience
where you can try out different styles
and different hypotheses
and in so doing you paradoxically
introduce
the right kind of uncertainty
[Music]
that about different styles of
engagement and
who you are and who you are talking to
and by relaxing that precision
you enable um you give the patient
or the or the naughty team that's become
too siloed
the latitude to explore other ways or
other ways
of behaving so i would imagine that most
of um
most of the tried and trusted in
[Music]
procedures um to get teams into a co
into a co-transformative space and
you know use one of or more of those
mechanisms
what would active inference be bring to
the table it would just
bring the the narrative that
all everybody you're trying to get to
talk to each other
um can come to share so they can see
through the process of becoming um
more collaborative or exchanging ideas
more fluently or working to
working with the cert with the same
lexicon or mechanics or
code and it will enable them
it will enable them to um
to having the same narrative will
actually shape their prior space
um and understand the mechanics of
actually enlarging
the the hypothesis space in terms of
inter interaction styles
so that was an incredibly hand waving
answer but
it was in part informed by almost
well my understanding of the question um
from the point of view of the
psychiatrist who wants to transform
the way that a patient relates to to her
to her world oh and drugs can help
and i mean that literally those drugs
um that are responsible
neurobiologically for setting the
precision
if you can temporarily suspend the
in order to reveal other
latent a priory hypotheses in terms of
the way that
i am or the way that i interact and the
way that i behave or the way that i
perceive
that can actually have long lasting
effects and that on bringing those
other hypotheses to the table in the
moment in subsequent interactions
so perhaps the most compelling example
of this um which is trending at the
moment is the use of
psilocybin assistive therapy
particularly in terminal care
so you know if you know you're going to
die of cancer in the next six months
there are certain hypotheses that are
brought to bear in terms of
how i would expect to feel um and
how i engage with the world and how i
engage with my loved ones
as a dying person who is near death and
the ultimate loss
those are not necessarily the best or
most functional
hypotheses or ways of being there are
other ways of dying gracefully and
gloriously
but to get at them sometimes having a
you know a
um a managed um
challenge to your 5 ht 2a receptors via
things like psilocybin and other related
drugs
just allows you to um suspend for a
moment your very precise beliefs about
the kind of thing i am
and allows you to experience other ways
of being and perceiving
which can be very useful when it comes
to just trying out other hypotheses and
you know in your this is your cancer
journey but
you know one can also imagine similar
scenarios when you get locked in
to a particular way of um interacting
with uh
either within a team or to between teams
in a larger organization
so that would mean you have to go on a
retreat and take lots of magic mushrooms
never thought i would hear from you
professor fristen but there we have it
drugs for teams thank you for this
excellent interval with dot-coms unit
we're going to take another five-minute
break and we'll return
for the final session for dot tools
thanks again
everyone and we'll see you in five
minutes